Using your personal informationHow we use your personal information

Please read this privacy notice to understand how we use and protect the information you provide to us.Your information will be held by The Co-operative Bank p.l.c., also trading as smile, Britannia andPlatform (and known as “the Bank”).

Data protection law and how it protects you

Data protection law requires us to manageall personal information in accordance withthe data protection principles. In particular,we are required to process your personalinformation fairly and lawfully. This means youare entitled to know how we intend to use anyinformation you provide. You can then choosewhether you want to give it to us so we canprovide the product or service you require.All our employees are responsible formaintaining customer confidentiality.We provide training and education to allemployees to remind them about theirobligations. In addition, our policies andprocedures are regularly audited and reviewed.

1\. Where we obtain the information

Your personal information will be held securelyby the Bank so we can (either now or in thefuture) manage your relationship with us.This will include information you provide whenyou apply to us, and any additional informationprovided by you or others in various ways,including:1.1.In applications, emails and letters, duringtelephone calls and conversations inbranch and online, when registeringfor services, in customer surveys,when you participate in competitions andpromotions, through our website includingour mobile app and during financialreviews and interviews.1.2.From analysis (for example, the amount,frequency, location, origin and recipient)of your payments and other transactions,from your use of our services and what weknow from operating your account.1.3.Information we receive from our businesspartners and from other organisationssuch as credit reference agencies and fraudprevention agencies.

1.4.Through your use of different technologieswhen accessing information about youraccounts with us (such as IP addresses,IMEI numbers, web browsers, biometricdata and computer operating systems).We will not retain your personal information forlonger than is necessary for the maintenanceof your account, or for legal or regulatoryrequirements. The Bank retains personal datarelating to accounts for a maximum of sevenyears to meet our legal requirements, thoughfor certain product related documentationretention periods vary. If you have anyquestions relating to the retention periodsapplied to your data please contact the DataProtection Officer at the following email address

data.protection@co-operativebank.co.uk

The Bank may occasionally collect and holdpersonal information which is highly sensitive innature, under data protection law this is knownas special categories of data.This is usually only related to health matterswhich you bring to our attention to help usunderstand how best we can support you in themanagement of your account(s).If you give us personal information aboutsomeone else (such as a joint applicant) thenyou should not do so without their permissionand you must ensure they are made aware ofthe content of this notice.Where information is provided by you aboutsomeone else, or someone else disclosesinformation about you, it will be added to anypersonal information which is already held byus and it will be used in the ways described inthis privacy notice.

2\. The personal information we collectand process

The Bank will only gather and process therelevant type and amount of personalinformation required, allowing us to help youopen and then manage your accounts with us.The categories of personal information that wecollect (or create on your behalf) are:

Category Some examples of theinformation in this category

Name data

• Title• Surname\*• Forename\*• Previous surname\*

Personal data

• Date of Birth\*• National Insurance Number\*• Gender

Residence data

• Residential address\*• Tax residency\*• Previous residential address

Contact data

• Home telephone number• Mobile telephone number• Correspondence addresses

Employmentdata

(only used ataccount openingstage)

• Employment status• Employer’s address• Salary details

Account leveldata

(created to allowan account tooperate)

• Account number• Card number• IBAN/Swift number

Digital data

• IP address• IMEI• Internet banking username• Biometric Data

Security data

• Internet passwords/codes• Mobile Banking passwords/codes• Telephone Bankingpasswords/codes\*Certain data items we collect throughout thelifecycle of an account are mandatory to allowus to meet our regulatory requirements,and will be shared with government bodiesand for fraud prevention activities as describedwithin this notice. While the list above is notexhaustive those marked with an asteriskare mandatory.

3\. How we use your information

We will use the personal information we holdabout you for the following administrativeactivities:

How we use yourinformationThe basis on which weuse your information

• To develop our productsand services• To manage our productdelivery• To perform marketingand sales• To manage yourapplications• Assessing lending andinsurance risks• Customer modellingand statistical trendanalysis with the aimof developing andimproving productsand services

• Fulfilling contracts• Our legitimate interests• Our legal obligation• Your consent

• Managing yourrelationship with us• Updating, consolidationand improving theaccuracy of our records• Arrears and debtrecovery activities• Undertakingtransactional analysis• Process payments

• Fulfilling contracts• Our legitimate interests• Our legal obligation

• Crime detection,prevention andprosecutions• Fraud prevention andinvestigation• Anonymising andaggregating personalinformation for securityreasons

• Our legitimate interests• Our legal obligation

• Testing new systems andchecking upgrades toexisting systems• Our legitimate interests

• Profiling for marketingpurposes• Evaluating theeffectiveness ofmarketing and formarket research andtraining• Administrating offers,competitions andpromotions

• Your consent• Our legitimate interests

By processing this information it enables us tobetter understand your needs and operate youraccounts in the efficient way you expect.Your information will also be used for otherpurposes for which you give your specificpermission, or, in very limited circumstances,when required by law.

4\. When we will share your information

We will treat your personal information asprivate and confidential but will disclose itoutside the Bank if:4.1. Allowed by this agreement;4.2. You consent;4.3. Needed by our agents, advisers or othersinvolved in running accounts and servicesfor you or collecting what you owe us;4.4. Needed by sub-contractors to help usmanage your records;4.5. HM Revenue \& Customs or otherauthorities require it;4.6. The law, regulatory bodies or the publicinterest permits or requires it;4.7. Required by us or others to investigate orprevent crime;4.8. Needed by market research companies toassist us in providing better products andservices to you;4.9. Needed by any other parties connectedwith your account (including guarantors,power of attorney representatives);4.10. Needed by organisations who provideus with a service, on the understandingthey keep your information secure andconfidential, unless you tell us not to;4.11. Required as part of our duty to protectyour accounts, for example we arerequired to disclose your information tothe UK Financial Services CompensationScheme (FSCS).We will always ensure your information remainssafe and secure. Please go to

co-operativebank.co.uk/global/third-parties

to see our supplier register.

5\. Using your information to help preventterrorism and crime

The government also requires us to screenapplications which are made to us, to ensurewe are complying with the international fightagainst terrorism and other criminal activities.As a result of this, we will need to discloseinformation to government bodies.

6\. Sharing your information to assist withasset buying and selling

We may in the future wish to sell, transfer ormerge part or all of our business or assets, orany associated rights or interests, or to acquirea business or enter into a merger. If so,we will disclose your personal information to apotential buyer, transferee, or merger partner orseller and their advisers, so long as they agreeto keep the information confidential and to useit only to consider the possible transaction.

If the transaction goes ahead, the buyers,transferee or merger partner will use or discloseyour personal information in the same way asset out in this notice.

7\. Sharing your information with creditcard providers

If you hold a credit or debit card with us,we will share transaction details with ourscheme provider Visa. Please go to

co-operativebank.co.uk/global/third-parties

to see our supplier register.

8\. Sharing your personal informationbetween first and second charge lenders

If you have a secured loan or mortgage with us,we will need to share information with otherlenders who also hold a charge on yourproperty. Please go to

co-operativebank.co.uk/global/third-parties

to see our supplier register.

9\. Sharing information betweenjoint applicants

When you open a joint account or product,this will mean your personal information will beshared with the other applicant. For example,transactions made by you will be seen by yourjoint account holder and vice-versa.

10\. How we share your personal informationwith and use credit reference agencies

Credit Reference Agencies (CRAs) collect andmaintain information about consumers’ andbusinesses’ credit behaviour. This includesElectoral Register, fraud prevention, and creditinformation – including details of previousapplications and the conduct of your accounts– and public information such as County CourtJudgments, Decrees and Bankruptcies.The information we and other organisationsprovide to CRAs about you, your financialassociates and your business (if you have one)will be provided to other organisations andused by them and us to:10.1. Help make decisions, for example when:10.1.1. Checking details on applicationsfor credit and credit-related orother facilities;10.1.2. Managing credit and credit-relatedaccounts or facilities;10.1.3. Recovering debt;10.1.4. Checking details on proposals andclaims for all types of insurance;10.2. Detect and prevent crime, fraud andmoney laundering;10.3. Check your credit history;10.4. Verify your identity if you, or someoneis financially linked with you, applies forservices;

10.5. Trace your whereabouts, and10.6. Undertake research, statistical analysisand systems testing.If we need to make a credit decision when youapply for a service e.g. mortgage, personal loan,credit card or current account, or to review theamount of credit we provide under an existingagreement, such as an overdraft, your recordswill be searched along with those of anyonewho is financially associated with you,such as your spouse or partner.The CRA will keep a record of this search andplace a “footprint” on your credit file, whetheror not the application proceeds.When we receive an application from abusiness, we will perform a search with a CRAon the individual company directors or partnersand any associated guarantors.We will also provide details of your account andhow you conduct it to CRAs, including if youborrow money, and do not repay the agreedamount of money in full and on time back tothe Bank. If you fall behind with your agreedpayments and a full payment or satisfactoryproposal is not received within 28 days of aformal demand being issued, then a defaultnotice will be recorded with the CRAs.Similar information will also be given aboutyour other lending/credit relationships with us.Any records shared with CRAs will remain onfile for six years after your account is closed,whether it has been settled by you or as a resultof a default. Other organisations will see thesesearches and updates if you apply for creditin the future, and may affect your ability toborrow from other lenders.If you apply for or hold an account in jointnames, or tell us you have a spouse or financialassociate, a financial association will be createdbetween your records, including any previousand subsequent names used by you.This means your financial affairs may betreated as affecting each other. These links willremain on your files until such a time as youor your partner is successful in applying for adisassociation with the CRAs to break the link.You must ensure you have their agreement todisclose information about them. Searches willbe made on all joint applicants, and searchfootprints will be left on all applicants’ records.You have a right to apply to the CRAs for a copyof your file. We carry out most of our creditsearches using Experian, but details of how youmanage your account(s) will be disclosed to allCRAs. The information they hold may not bethe same and there is a small fee you will needto pay to each agency you apply to.

You can find out more about the CRAs andthe Credit Reference Agency Privacy Notice(CRAIN) on the websites below. The CRAINincludes details about:• Who the credit reference agencies are• Their role as fraud prevention agencies• The data they hold• How they use this data• How they share personal information• How long they can keep data• Your data protection rightsThere are three main credit reference agencies:TransUnionConsumer Services, TransUnionP.O. Box 491, Leeds LS3 1WZCall 0330 024 7574Visit www.transunion.co.uk

Equifax PLCCredit File Advice Centre,P.O. Box 10036, Leicester LE3 4FSCall 0333 321 4043Visit www.equifax.co.uk

ExperianConsumer Help Service,P.O. Box 8000, Nottingham NG80 7WFCall 0344 481 8000Visit www.experian.co.uk11\. How we use Fraud Prevention Agencies

We have systems which protect our customersand ourselves against fraud and other crime.Customer information can be used to preventcrime and trace those responsible. We willshare your personal information from yourapplication with Fraud Prevention Agencies.If false or inaccurate information is providedand fraud is identified, details of this fraud willbe passed to these agencies.Law enforcement agencies may also accessand use this information to prevent fraud andmoney laundering, for example, when:11.1. Checking details on applications for creditand credit related or other facilities;11.2. Managing credit and credit relatedaccounts or facilities;11.3. Recovering debt;11.4. Checking details on proposals and claimsfor all types of insurance.We and other organisations will access and usethe information recorded by fraud preventionagencies from other countries.

Fraud prevention agencies can hold yourpersonal data for different periods of time, andif you are considered to pose a fraud or moneylaundering risk, your data can be held for up tosix years.If we, or a fraud prevention agency, determinethat you pose a fraud or money laundering risk,we may refuse to provide the services andfinancing you have requested, or to employ you,or we may stop providing existing services to you.A record of any fraud or money laundering riskwill be retained by the fraud prevention agencies,and may result in others refusing to provideservices, financing or employment to you.If you want to receive details of the fraudprevention agencies from whom we obtain andwith whom we record information about you,contact us at:Fraud OperationsThe Co-operative Bank p.l.c.P.O. Box 300Delf HouseSkelmersdaleWN8 6NYFor further information please see

www.cifas.org.uk/fpn orwww.nhunter.co.uk/privacypolicy/12\. How we manage information collectedon your bank account, mortgageaccount and credit card statements

Transactions which you or a joint accountor card holder makes will create personalinformation that will appear on your statement.By making such transactions you give us yourconsent to process this information.

13\. Individual RightsRight to be informed – you have the right tobe informed about what we do with the datawe have about you.

Right to access – you have the right to accesspersonal data and supplementary informationthat is held about you by the Bank.

Right to rectification – you are entitledto have your personal data rectified if it isinaccurate or incomplete.

Right to erasure – you have the right torequest the removal or deletion of yourpersonal data (also known as “right to beforgotten”), where there is no compellingreason for the Bank to continue processingthis data. The Bank can refuse your requestwhere there is a legal obligation to hold theinformation. This will be further explained toyou upon making a request.

Right to restrict processing – you have theright to restrict the processing of your personaldata in the following circumstances (i) whereyou contest the accuracy of the personal data.

The Bank will restrict the processing until youhave verified the accuracy of the personal data(ii) where you have objected to the processing,and until the Bank has considered thelegitimate grounds to override the processing.(iii) when processing is unlawful (iv) where theBank no longer needs the personal data but yourequire the data to establish, exercise or defenda legal claim.

Right to data portability – this right allowsyou to move copy or transfer your personal dataeasily from one IT environment to another in asafe and secure way, without hindranceto usability.

Right to object – you have the right to objectto processing for direct marketing (includingprofiling) purposes. The Bank can refuse thisright where there is a legitimate interest forprocessing your personal data. This will befurther explained to you upon makinga request.

Rights related to automated decisionmaking including profiling – you have theright to object to automated decision makingwithout any human involvement, and to theprofiling of your personal data. The Bank onlycarry out this type of processing where it isnecessary to enter into a contract with us orwhere you have provided us with your consent,for example when applying for a loanor mortgage. To invoke your rights or manageyour personal marketing preferences,please log in to your personal account online,alternatively call us on 03457 212 212~ or callinto your nearest branch.

14\. Legitimate Interest Tests

As an essential part of our business, the Bankcollects, holds and manages (“processes”) datarelating to our customers. The data protectionregulation recognises in certain circumstances,processing may be deemed “necessary for thepurposes of the legitimate interests pursued bythe controller or by a third party, except wheresuch interests are overridden by the interests orfundamental rights and freedoms of the datasubject which require protection”.To validate a specific purpose for data processingis indeed legitimate; the Bank will conduct alegitimate interests test. This will serve to balanceour rights to process the data against the dataprotection rights of the affected individuals.In making the decision whether or not legitimateinterests may apply in each circumstance, wewill ensure the balance of rights always favoursthe individual customer, and the processing willnot cause the individual unwarranted harm bymeans of discrimination, damage to reputation,financial loss, and loss of confidentiality or othersignificant economic or social disadvantage.

15\. Using companies to process yourinformation outside of the EEA

All countries in the European Economic Area(EEA), which includes the UK, have similarstandards of legal protection for your personalinformation. We will process payments throughother financial institutions such as banks andthe worldwide payments system operated by theSWIFT organisation if, for example, you make aCHAPS payment or a foreign payment.Those external organisations may process andstore your personal information abroad andmay have to disclose it to foreign authoritiesto help them in their fight against crime andterrorism. If these are based outside of the EEA,your personal information may not be protectedto standards similar to those in the UK.

16\. How we may contact youUsing your personal information to contactyou about products and services

If you have given us permission, we may contactyou for marketing purposes, by mail, telephone,email or text message about products andservices available from us. In addition, we mayalso contact you about products and servicesfrom other selected companies, which webelieve will be of interest to you or benefit youfinancially. You have the right to withdraw,object to, or change your marketing preferencesat any time, online via your personal account,calling us on 03457 212 212~ or by visiting yournearest branch.We promise not to contact you abouteverything – only if we think it could beappropriate and relevant to you, such aspreferential savings opportunities, accountupgrades or special offers. This contact maycontinue after your relationship with us ends.

Passing your information to othercompanies for their own direct marketing

Unless you have given us your permission,we will not contact you on behalf of third parties,or pass your details onto them directly.

Using your contact information for servicecontact

Making sure we deliver excellent customerservice is very important to us, and to do thisvarious methods of communication will beused when sending you information about youraccount. Most of the time you will be contactedby letter or telephone, but you will also be sentupdates by text message or email when it isdeemed to be appropriate.

17\. When you apply for and use ourproducts and servicesUsing credit scoring

When you apply for credit, an automated systemknown as credit scoring will be used whenconsidering whether to agree the borrowing.It is a method of assessing your likely conductof an account based on a range of data,including the conduct of previous similaraccounts. It is a system widely used by creditproviders to help make fair and informeddecisions on lending.Credit scoring takes account of informationfrom three sources; the information you provideon your application, information provided byCRAs and information which may already beheld about you by us e.g. existing accountinformation. A credit scoring system will considerinformation from these sources, to make anoverall assessment of your application. The creditscoring methods used are regularly tested toensure they remain fair, effective and unbiased.Using a credit scoring system helps us to lendresponsibly. If you submit an application and itis declined through this automated process,you can contact us within 21 days to have thedecision reconsidered. You also have the right toask that the decision is not made based solelyusing an automated credit scoring system.

How we check your identity

We will ask you to provide physical formsof identity verification when you open youraccount. Additionally, we will search CRA filesin assessing your application. The CRA alsogives us other details and information from theElectoral Register to verify your identity.The CRA keeps a record of our search, whetheror not your application proceeds. Our search inthis instance is not seen or used by the Bank toassess your ability to obtain credit.

Undertaking anti-money laundering andfraud checks

To comply with money laundering requirements,there are times when we will need to confirm(or reconfirm) the name and address ofour customers.As part of the processing of your personal data,decisions may be made by automated means.This means we may automatically decide thatyou pose a fraud or money laundering risk if:• Our processing reveals your behaviourto be consistent with that of knownfraudsters or money launderers; oris inconsistent with your previoussubmissions; or• You appear to have deliberately hiddenyour true identity.

Obtaining information about you and otherpersonal details

When you apply for a mortgage or furtherborrowing it will be necessary to obtainreferences, details of your existing financialcommitments, and any other informationrequired to assess or review lending risks,to recover debts, and to prevent or detect fraud.Where applicable, your current and previousemployers, accountant, landlord, lender, bank,insurance or pension company will becontacted to obtain this information. In limitedcircumstances these references may needto be obtained after you open your account.This may be for regulatory purposes, or if thelending decision needs to be reviewed.Your permission to obtain these references willtherefore continue to apply after your accounthas been opened. It will also be necessary toobtain information or documentation fromyour solicitor relating to any work they carryout either on your or our behalf.

Recording phone calls

We will monitor or record phone calls with youin case we need to check we have carried outyour instructions correctly, to resolve queries orissues, for regulatory purposes, to help improveour quality of service, and to help detect orprevent fraud or other crimes.Conversations will also be monitored for stafftraining purposes.We also use interactive voice responsetechnology to help us manage your accountand provide you with services you require.

Using information on social networking sites

As part of our ongoing commitment tounderstanding our customers better andto improve our services, we will researchcomments and opinions made public on socialnetworking sites such as Twitter and Facebook.

Obtaining a copy of your information

Under data protection law, you have the rightto access the personal information we holdabout you. Additionally, you have the right torestrict and object to certain data processing.To request access to the information, and/or toinform us about a data restriction or objection,please write to (please ensure the request issigned to allow us to verify your identity):Subject Access Request TeamP.O. Box 638SalfordM5 0JQYou can also send us a secure message throughyour accounts section online, alternatively callus on 03457 212 212~ or call in to yournearest branch.

18\. Your right to rectify and erase data wehold about you

It is important the information we hold aboutyou is accurate and up to date at all times,as holding incorrect information can have animpact on what the Bank shares with thirdparties such as the CRAs, taxation authoritiesand fraud prevention authorities.If you believe we are holding any informationrelating to you which is incorrect please contactus to let us know what is wrong, and we willwork with you to put it right.

19\. How we protect your information

We are committed to taking appropriatetechnical, physical and organisationalmeasures to protect customer and colleaguepersonal information against unauthorisedaccess, unlawful processing, accidental loss ordamage, and unauthorised destruction.We use secure servers to enable you to makeenquiries or access your account information,which encrypts your information before it issent to us. We also take appropriate measuresto ensure the information disclosed to us iskept secure, accurate and up-to-date and keptonly for as long as necessary for the purposeswhich it is used.We limit access to our internal systems whichhold personal information to a selected groupof authorised users who are given access tosuch systems through the use of a uniqueidentifier and password. Access to personalinformation is limited to and provided toindividuals for the purpose of performing theirwork duties.

20\. Cookies

Cookies are used to store small amounts ofinformation on your computer, which allowscertain information from your web browser tobe collected. Cookies are widely used on theinternet. Please refer to our Cookies Policy forfurther information at co-operativebank.co.uk/global/privacy-and-cookies21\. Changes to privacy notice

We will update this notice to reflect changesto our information practices. If we make anymaterial changes we will notify you by meansof a notice on our website prior to the changebecoming effective.We encourage you to periodically review

co-operativebank.co.uk/global/privacy-and-cookies for the latest information on ourprivacy practices.

MKT90619 WEB

01/2021

22\. Complaints about how we process yourpersonal information

We know sometimes things go wrong, andhere at the Bank we really value your feedback.Letting us know when you are not happy withour products and services provides us with theopportunity to put it right as quickly as possibleand helps us to improve our service for allour customers.Our promise is to:• Treat your complaint fairly and promptly;• Try to resolve complaints straight away,when you first contact us; and• Keep you informed of our progress.You can contact us via email atcomplaints@co-operativebank.co.ukAlternatively, you can call us on 03457 212 212~,call in to your nearest branch or write to us at:Customer ResponseThe Co-operative Bank p.l.c.P.O. Box 1011 Balloon StManchesterM60 4EPThe Bank would always suggest that anycommunication with us is by a secure methodand would not encourage use of unsecuredemail if you are including personal information.If you still wish to contact us by email and/orrequest an answer by email that may containpersonal information we would make youaware of the following:• We use Transport Layer Security (TLS) toencrypt and protect email traffic.If your mail server does not support TLS,you should be aware that any emails you

send to us, or emails you request from us,may not be protected in transit;• The Bank may choose not to reply withcertain types of information via email,therefore please include alternativecontact details; and• Please be aware, we cannot accept fileattachments that are larger than 20MB.

23\. Contact details for the Bank DataProtection Officer

If you wish to contact the Data ProtectionOfficer in relation to any questions orconfidential queries about this privacy notice orthe information we hold and process about you,please emaildata.protection@co-operativebank.co.ukor write to us at:The Data Protection OfficerThe Co-operative Bank p.l.c.P.O. Box 1011 Balloon StreetManchesterM60 4EP

24\. Contact details for the InformationCommissioner’s Office

If you wish to contact the InformationCommissioner for advice or to complain aboutthe way you believe your information is used,please find their address and website below.The Information Commissioner’s OfficeWycliffe HouseWater LaneWilmslowSK9 5AFWebsite: www.ico.org.uk

Please call 03457 212 212\* ~ if you would like to receive thisinformation in an alternative format such as large print, audioor Braille.

The Co-operative Bank p.l.c. is authorised by the Prudential Regulation Authority and regulated by the Financial Conduct Authorityand the Prudential Regulation Authority (No.121885). The Co-operative Bank, Platform, smile and Britannia are trading names ofThe Co-operative Bank p.l.c., P.O. Box 101, 1 Balloon Street, Manchester M60 4EP. Registered in England and Wales No.990937.Credit facilities are provided by The Co-operative Bank p.l.c. and are subject to status and our lending policy. The Bank reserves theright to decline any application for an account or credit facility. The Co-operative Bank p.l.c. subscribes to the Standards of LendingPractice which are monitored by the Lending Standards Board.\*Calls to 03 numbers cost the same as calls to numbers starting with 01 and 02. Calls may be monitored or recorded for securityand training purposes.~Lines open 8am to 8pm, 7 days a week.Information Updated January 2021.

co-operativebank.co.uk
